okay the next segment is going to
introduce some of the linguistic
background as well as some of the
mathematical background needed for this
class so as I told you at the beginning
of the class we're going to look at NLP
from a slightly more linguistic
perspective than other courses on this
topic so I won't first to introduce you
to the basic of basics of linguistics a
little bit of it is not going to be even
very useful for this class but I wanted
to get the coherent picture of the main
topics in linguistics so let's look at
some of the issues that arise in an Opie
that have their origins in linguistics
community for example the idea of a
constituent so what is a constituent in
linguistics it is a unit of the syntax
of a sentence that has a specific whole
so for example if I have the sentence
children eat pizza or the sadness they
eat pizza in both cases I have the
underline fragment indicating the
subject of the sentence
those can be replaced with each other
and the sentence would still be
grammatical or I can say my cousin's
neighbors children eat pizza as you can
see all of those three underlined
expressions can be the subject of the
sentence therefore they have something
in common what you turn out to be is
that they're all noun phrases because
they can be all subjects of a sentence
you can see that the length actually
doesn't really matter and the fact that
the second word is not even now it's a
pronoun also doesn't matter what's most
important is that all those three items
can be the subjects of the same sentence
now you can even have instances where
the subject of a sentence is not
explicitly mentioned for example if I
tell you eat pizza I mean that you
should be eating the pizza so you are
the implicit subject of the sentence but
because of the way I formulated the
sentence is an imperative as an order
the subject is not explicitly marked we
also need to know about the things about
collocations so collocations are groups
of words that appear more frequently
together than you would expect by chance
and typically have some specific
meaning for example even though the word
strong is a synonym of powerful in most
contexts we can say that some beer is
strong but we cannot say that that beer
is powerful so two synonyms cannot be
always interchangeable an even funnier
example you can say that this is my big
sister but you cannot say this is my
large sister even though I begin larger
often synonyms now an example that I was
looking for in the news has to do with
the word rise versus ascend it turns out
that in the past when I first did this
experiment maybe 10 years ago people
would never say stocks ascend instead
they would say stocks to rise all the
time there were 225 thousand hits on
Google for the former and only 47 of
this latter one but when I did this
experiment for this class it turns out
that stocks ascend is now a much more
acceptable collocation they will in fact
fifty seven thousand instances of that
on Google but still we have a major
difference in the frequency of those two
collocations in ten to one ratio so how
do we get this kind of linguistic
knowledge in the NOP system well they're
essentially two approaches one is some
sort of manual rules that tell you well
a big sister means this and large system
is something completely different and
you have to encode those as part of the
knowledge of the system by hand or you
can automatically acquire this kind of
rules for large text collections also
known as core part so what kind of
knowledge about language is needed well
there's all the areas of linguistics
phonetics and phonology which are the
study of sounds for example what are
consonants and vowels and which
consonants are stops versus fricatives
morphology which is the study of word
components for example in the word
impossible M is a prefix that means
negation and impossible means something
that is not possible
syntax is the study of
sentence and phrase structure what is
the subject of the sentence what is the
object what is the verb lexical
semantics is the study of the meanings
of individual words compositional
semantics is how to combine words and
segments of sentences and to understand
the meaning of the combined sentence
pragmatics is how to accomplish goals
and then discourse conventions is about
dealing with units of text that are
larger than single utterances or single
sentences for example you can have a
multi sentential paragraph where each
additional sentence somehow he first to
the first sentence by using pronouns and
other forms of reference there will be a
separate lecture on the different levels
of language later on this class now from
computer science we can look at some
techniques like finite state automata so
finite state automaton is a machine that
consists of states and transitions one
of the states is the start state and you
can also have one or more final or
accept states in this example here state
zero is the start state it's indicated
by a solid circle the solid line circle
and state number thirteen is an accept
state and that is denoted by the double
circle the transitions go as follows
from state zero to state one you have
the letter C from state 1 to state 2 you
have the letter A from state 2 to state
2 you have the letter T then there is a
space from 3 to 4 and so on so the whole
automaton here is used to encode the
sequence of three words cat space cats
space dogs another otamatone known as a
transducer can be then combined with the
previous automaton to perform some sort
of phonological or morphological
analysis of the sentence so the second
automaton here starts in state zero and
then it has multiple paths so let's look
at them in detail the top path
three consecutive edges the first edge
converts C to a zero whereas zero
indicates the empty string in this
example then the next edge is from one
to two it takes as input the letter A
and it produces the empty string as
output and finally the third transition
goes from state 2 to state 3 it needs in
a T the letter T and it produces a
capital N and then it goes to state
number 3 which is an acceptable final
state so if we perform a specific
operation on the two automata that you
can see on the screen that specific
operation is called composition what is
going to happen is that we're going to
read the seed a and the T from the input
on the top and convert that sequence
into the sequence empty string followed
by empty string followed by capital n so
in a sense we did a very simple
morphological analyzer slash part of
speech tagger we labeled the word cat as
a noun and if the input string cat had
stopped right there we would have been
in an accept state number 3 and we would
have just produced the noun label and
stopped however our input contains three
words and the middle automaton has the
capability of processing all those three
words and producing the correct labels
for them so let's see if we can trace it
so we already did the part where we look
at CA T and we label this as a noun and
now the next symbol on the input is a
space well the space takes us from state
3 to state 0 and doesn't produce any
output so we can essentially go back to
the beginning then we have a see a TS in
the second automaton that takes us to
the same path as before and we produce
an end going from state 0 to state 1 to
state 2 and to state 3 but then s now
takes us to state 6 but now we're going
to produce a P on the output tape and
that will tell us that the word cats is
a noun plural
we could stop here but since there is
more input to process we have to go back
from state six to the beginning state
zero the input is an empty string I got
a space in this case and the output is
an empty string let me go back to state
zero and we have now the word dogs so
this is process by going from state zero
to state four then to state five then to
state three in which case we output the
letter n then we have one more letter in
the input the letter S which gets
translated into a capital P and now at
this point both the input string and the
so called transducer are in an accept
state therefore we can stop and we can
just produce the output that you see at
the bottom of the screen so let's read
it carefully here the output has two
labels on each edge the first label
comes from the input and the second
label comes from the transducer so if we
read it left to right by only focusing
on the first label on each edge we're
going to get the original string which
is cat space cat's space dogs now if we
read the second label in each transition
we're going to produce the output of
this para speech tagger so let's try to
do this here empty string empty string
capital n which is the label for cat
followed by empty string empty string
empty string capital n capital P which
is the label for the word cats as a noun
plural followed by a few empty strings
followed by a capital N and capital P
which is the label for the plural noun
dogs so this point in time the
transducer has finished its work and we
can just produce the output which
consists of the second labels on every
transition so n n P and P this was just
a small illustration how techniques that
come from theoretical computer science
such as finite state automata are used
in natural language processing there are
other areas of theoretical computer
science that find that are useful in
natural language processing in addition
to automata
the kind I just showed you there's also
pushdown automata which I used to
process more sophisticated grammars and
in a few weeks you will see how they
work we also need to import some
techniques from computer science that
deal with grammar specifically regular
grammars context-free grammars
context-sensitive grammars and some
other kinds of grammars which again will
be covered in this course later on this
semester there are also issues related
to the complexity of the different
algorithms and for example how long does
it take to process an input of a certain
size and finally there's aspects of
programming such as dynamic programming
dynamic programming is a specific
algorithm that is used to produce an
output that depends on the sequence on
the input and it's much more efficient
than trying all the possible
combinations on the input so we will
talk about dynamic programming later in
this class now in addition to
linguistics and computer science there
are areas in and opie that originate in
mathematics and statistics the whole use
of probabilities to indicate that
different sentences are likely to a
different extent the use of statistical
models hypothesis testing linear algebra
as well as optimization and numerical
methods we're going to see some of those
techniques in action later this semester
as well some additional mathematical and
computational tools that are popular in
natural language processing include
language models which are used to
determine the probability of a certain
sequence of symbols or words estimation
methods context-free grammars for trees
hidden Markov models or conditional
random fields for sequences and then
also different statistical models such
as different generative and
discriminative models and maximum
entropy models some techniques on
statistics that I use the natural
language processing our brief dimension
here one is the so-called vector space
representation for word sense
disambiguation which we're going to talk
about in a cup of weeks the noisy
channel model for machine translation
I'm going to illustrate those two here
at the bottom of the slide the left-hand
side shows you how different documents
can be represented as vectors in a
vector space so we have here two
documents D 1 and D 2 and a query Q oh
all three of those are represented as
vectors and we can determine which of
the two documents do you want or D 2 is
more similar to the query Q by looking
at the angle between that document and
the query so the angle between D 1 and Q
is alpha the angle between D 2 and Q is
Theta and in this case it's pretty
obvious that theta is a larger angle
than alpha and therefore a document 1 is
actually a better match to the query Q
the example on the right is the
so-called noisy channel model for
machine translation it is based on an
idea that originated in speech
processing and the idea is very simple
we assume that when we have two
languages and we want to translate
between them we assume that one of the
languages is an encoded version of the
other language so if we want to
translate some text from French to
English we are going to try to identify
which string in English is most likely
given the French string and this is then
converted using the Bayesian theorem
into the second expression on the right
and then it's also simplified into the
third expression on the right knowing
that the probability of the French
sentence does not change when you change
the English sentence so you can just
assume that for ranking purposes the
sentence in English that maximizes the
conditional probability of e given F can
be computed the same way even if you
didn't know the value of the probability
of the French settlers and finally the
third technique that is used in natural
language processing that originates in
statistics is the so called a random
walk method a random walk method takes a
graph and uses what is known as a Monte
Carlo simulation to label the nodes of
the graph using different values so this
is useful for tasks in natural language
processing such as sentiment analysis
where you have as input the sentence
that can be either positive or negative
and then you want to label some
additional sentences as either a
negative or positive by looking at the
examples that you have seen so far there
are some techniques in natural language
processing that originated in artificial
intelligence and I'm going to list just
a few here those include logic
specifically first-order logic and
predicate calculus those are ways to
represent the meaning of sentences the
idea of agents or essentially entities
that communicate with each other using
speech acts the idea of planning how do
you plan a sentence how do you decide
what goes into the sentence and how do
you decide that you want to render it in
a certain way and also a few more
techniques that we're going to focus a
little bit on later on this semester
such as constraint satisfaction and
machine learning so the next topic is
going to be an introduction to
linguistics as needed for this class